Hi, I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 2 of our 10 day Lip reading Challenge,
designed to help you develop and practice your lip reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and tricks on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity
to relationships in all areas of your life.
You probably guessed from the thumbnail
that the answer to the question from day 1 is: Banjo.
The word banjo is very similar to mango.
Watch: banjo, mango.
If we were talking about music,
you probably wouldn't confuse these two words.
That's why context is super important
when you're lip reading.
Huge clues about context
come from the topic and the lingo
and vocabulary associated with that topic.
Context is also about where you are, who you're with,
what you're doing,
and what you're about to do.
And when you know the context, you can
anticipate which words will follow.
Be aware of the clues around you
and anticipate,
and you will become a speech reader!
Now you have the opportunity to
experience this for yourself.
We'll get some practice lip reading
P, B, and M sounds in sentences.
Keep in mind that the level
of difficulty is critical.
If it's too hard you won't learn as much
and you won't enjoy learning, either.
And I do want you to enjoy yourself.
In a lip reading class it's my job as the teacher
to manage the level of difficulty for you,
but because this is YouTube
and not an interactive class,
it's your job to find that
sweet spot of difficulty.
Please support your own learning and
take the time to do that if you need to.
I will show you how in a moment, but first let's
see how you do with the first group of sentences.
To begin with, I'm going to
say the sentence silently.
Then I'll give you some context and
say the sentence again silently.
Are you ready?
For the first three sentences,
the P, B, and M words are one of these:
There's your first clue about context!
Number 1
and the context is
and now number 1 again
Number 2
the context is
and number 2 again
Number 3
and the context is
Oh no, this is my favourite shirt.
number 3 again
So if you couldn't figure out what I was
saying for this first group of sentences,
Please stop now.
Go to the description
section below the video frame,
and follow the instructions
for what to do to make it easier.
And then make sure you come back!
For the next three sentences
the PBM word is one of these:
Number 4
the context is: Why I have allergies
number 4 again
Number 5
the context is
number 5 again
Number 6
the context is
and number 6 again
For the next group of sentences,
the P, B, or M word will be one of these:
and remember,
you would not be able to
tell these words apart in isolation,
if they weren't in a sentence.
But because you have the sentence ,
you'll be able to figure it out.
Number 7
The context is: Let's see
if my plumbing job worked.
number 7 again
Number 8
and the context is: I said this sentence
in day 1. It's about being afraid of being
chased by a wild animal.
Here's number 8 again:
Number 9
Context is: it's not about a banjo!
And I want seconds.
Here's number 9 again:
For the last group of sentences the
P,B or M word will be one of these:
This group will be slightly more difficult. You know what to do
if you can't figure it out, right?
Number 10.
and the context is: Something
that I might do in frustration.
number 10 again
Number 11.
and the context is:
an injury in this area
Number 12.
and the context is:
Something we did in the Grand Canyon.
number 12 again:
That's it for our lip reading practice today.
Can you let me know in the comments if the
context helped you to see the
words the second time around?
I just have a couple more things to cover.
I want you to keep in mind that this is all a matter of practice
to improve your skill level.
If you had difficulty with these sentences,
follow the directions to make it easier,
if you haven't already.
And return to this practice until you
feel like you've mastered the sentences.
I have a question for you.
How would you ask for information
about the context, if you needed it?
I personally wouldn't say,
“What are we talking about??”
because I feel like it would give the impression
that I wasn't paying attention to the conversation
How would you ask for information about context?
Tomorrow we're going to learn
about a new group of homophones.
So I'll see you then for day 3.
In the meantime, if you could like this video,
subscribe to my channel, and share it with others,
I'd really appreciate it.
Thank you! Bye!